[music]
YouTube.
Uh it's my great pleasure to introduce
you uh Professor Brian Cox. Uh welcome
in our uh humble podcast. Uh uh how are
you on this magnificent day?
>> Very well, thank you. Um we're we're
we're talking about um just a day before
I start doing my live shows again. So I
haven't done any for about two months.
We finished in Singapore just before the
summer in June. So, tomorrow we have a
little show in the UK where I try and we
make sure everything still works and I
try and remember what I'm talking about
before we come before we come to
Bratislava.
>> Yeah, you have some tries before you
come to Bratislava because in Bratislava
you are on September of 9th of
September. So,
>> yeah,
>> I've got a few days.
>> So, can you describe the show briefly,
the emergence show? because uh when we
are doing scientific or science outreach
shows in Slovaka is just we do a
presentation but this is something more
sophisticated. So describe how do you
think about
>> when I read about it it's more uh show
than some kind of presentation.
>> Yeah. I mean it's um it so over the
years I've um been lucky to do you know
bigger and bigger shows and so now in
Australia or in the UK or the US I I I
we can do you know venues that have
15,000 people in them and so the
question comes well how do you do that
because you can't just stand there with
an overhead projector or something like
that right [laughter] it's a big venue
so over the years we've developed these
shows that are based on big LED screens
but also So um the the sound is
important, the music is important, the
lighting is important.
>> So in that sense it's a a show but uh it
is still and I joke sometimes with the
audience is still a lecture in a sense.
I'm talking ultimately about discoveries
that are being made in the fields of um
c certainly astrophysics, astronomy but
also particle physics, cosmology and
biology. Um so so there's a there's an
element of lecture about it but it's
it's a show in the way that we produce
it. You know we have a lot of a lot of
tech there but it starts with um um to
in order to do something like that with
a very wide audience lots of
>> people from different backgrounds
scientific backgrounds. Um, so there
needs to be a story and and the story
for this show started with a book that I
became interested in that Kepler wrote
in 1610 sometime in 1610 and it's a book
called the six cornered snowflake and I
was introduced to it by a friend years
ago and I've always loved it because it
this is it's actually um so Kepler's
most famous for his laws of planetary
motion. It's in between the first and
second and third laws of planetary
motion where he decides to ask this
question which is why do snowflakes all
have six corners which is an extremely
good question and it's a question about
what we call today symmetry. It's it's
why why does the snowflake have that
symmetry? This is a 20th and 21st
century way of thinking about physics
and trying to look at symmetries,
patterns in nature and trying to explain
what what what's the origin of that
pattern, the deeper origin.
>> And so I start with that story because
um it's the beginnings of modern science
in many ways. So this is 1610, you know,
following that we have Newton's laws in
the 1680s and so on. And then off we go
to the 400 years later the p to the
picture that we have today. So it starts
with that story. So so um questions of
symmetry and questions of patterns are
important in the show. And also actually
which I find wonderful at the end of the
book Kepler says I don't know. I don't
know the answer.
>> That's pretty radical at the time. Um
but it's of course as as I as I say in
the show central to progress is the idea
that there are things that we don't know
and so I focus on the things we don't
know as well.
>> Interesting.
>> How do you find
>> sorry
>> you also have a show in Prague and
Kepler
derived his first two law in Prague. So
you can go and see the building where he
did this. start. So the show start the
graphics the question you asked earlier
it starts on the Charles Bridge impress
in a snowstorm. So we built the Charles
Bridge
>> uh not quite as it was in6009
actually because we had the statues on
it because I like the statues and I
found out the statues weren't there in
1609.
>> A later edition. Yeah.
>> Yeah. But other than that, it's the
Charles Bridge. And so the the whole
beginning of the show is is on a
recreation of the Charles Bridge
>> and you will have a unique view of
Charles Bridge without any tourist or
anybody because it's overcrowdedly
the snowstorm but there are the statues.
>> Yeah. Great. [laughter]
Uh and my question is how do you find uh
best format for a show like this? Did
you come up with few different ideas or
did you know from the start that this is
the format I want to do?
>> I I knew that I wanted to start with
Kepler and that story and I also wanted
to end with something to do with the
snowflake and everything it represents.
The the questions about symmetry, the
ideas that there are many things that we
don't know. In fact, every as you will
know every scientific question
ultimately ends with we don't know. Mhm.
>> I mean, we go to, you know, why are the
quantum fields the the way that they
are? Why is quantum field theory the way
that we describe the universe and so on?
Was there a beginnings to the universe?
I talk about all those things and the
answer is we don't know to all those
things. Um, so I knew that um and I also
knew that I wanted to talk about um the
history of science in particular,
this idea that there is new knowledge to
be gained. And it's really one of the um
one of the reasons that science really
took off at that point. Nothing much had
happened if you think about it. From
Aristotle all the way to Capernacus,
Kepler and then onwards to Newton. Not
much had happened, right? We hadn't
really generated very much new
knowledge. So what changed at the time?
What changed? One of the things that
changed is this idea that the ancient
Greeks didn't know everything, right? Is
the idea is extremely important.
>> So I knew that. Um but then the things
that I I build into the show. Um so for
example, the Vera Rubin Observatory is
just come online as I was writing the
show and those images those remarkable
high resolution images 3.2 to gigapixel
images of the sky
>> are really um revolutionizing the way
that we do cosmology at some level,
right? This avalanche of data. And so I
start you start plugging those things in
and I say I want to talk about that. I
want to talk about Vera Rubin. Um I one
the bit of research that I still do is
it involves black holes and quantum
information.
>> So I wanted to talk about that. So, so
you so you ultimately you weave a story
in but based around that basic idea of
Kepler and the beginnings of modern
science.
>> And is it the same when you write a book
like you know the first page and the
last page and then try to connect the
dots between
>> sort of no actually. So the last book I
wrote with a colleague of mine um who
I've worked with for decades Jeff
Foreshaw in Manchester was about black
holes. And one of the reasons we wrote
that book, probably the reason is that
we found them very interesting and and
wanted to know more about them and and
so so that one the reason that I write
books particularly with Jeff is because
it's there's things I want to find out
about. So [laughter] I want I want to
learn about something.
>> Okay.
>> And in the end we ended up getting a PhD
student and a posttock and actually
doing some re research into
>> into black holes and in particular
quantum information. But um that came
from just the desire to know to find out
new things. [clears throat]
>> So black holes are what brought me to
physics. During high school uh a friend
borrowed me a book about black holes
like it was a gel for light or something
like this.
>> And then I started doing theoretical
physics and I well basically pivoted to
something else than black holes. It was
quantum structure of space. But then I
realized it's also related to black
holes because quantum structure can
prevent small black holes from
completely evaporating and you can have
some sort of blankian
remnants. So which part of universe do
you think are the like the most
interesting? What do you pay attention
to in the universe? Are still black
holes or what are the big mysteries?
Well, that's interesting what you say
because as you'll know there's a debate
um the the black the so-called black
hole information paradox the one minute
version is that um uh Stephen Hawking
really begins this work I would say in
the 19 early 1970s by discovering that
black holes radiate which means that
they have a finite lifetime
>> which means that you can't you can't
avoid the question of what happens to
the things that fall in.
>> Yes. Um and so people like Leonard
Suskin and others Jared Tahft got very
exercised about this because Hawings
original calculation that that that
tells us that black holes have a
temperature and therefore glow and lose
energy said that if the black hole is
gone, if it radiates away and all that's
left is the radiation, there's no
information in that radiation at all. So
the suggestion was black holes erase
information which runs contrary to the
laws of quantum mechanics and I would
say all all the laws the known laws of
physics that we have information is
conserved preserved but apparently not
in black hole evaporation. So that led
to a 50-year program of research which
is still ongoing and as you said it's
interesting because you can take the
view which is your research I understand
that there's some remnant left over and
and in there is the information so it's
not destroyed it's preserved in some
kind of remnant which may be a the a
different sort of bubble universe or
something whatever it is there's loads
of ideas right about the remnants
>> the other idea which goes to people like
Jeff Pennington and others is that the
there the information ends up in the
Hawking radiation.
>> So um
>> so so the black hole does go but the
Hawking radiation contains the
information. That's really strange
because although the mathematics of
these calculations supports that idea,
um it's odd when you try to build a
physical picture of it. You think about
what a black hole is.
>> Then it's you could imagine falling into
a black hole across the horizon. Um in
just if we just talk about general
relativity, then you've crossed the
horizon. You're going to the end of
time, right? Time is going to end for
you. You'll be at the singularity.
That's that. you're not coming out. So
how it could be that the information
however scrambled it will be
>> ends up outside again in the radiation
physically how that happens is not known
and not agreed upon
>> or as you say you can have this picture
where there's a remnant left over which
I know some people um support as well.
So it's a it's a fascinating area of
research. I'll just say to finish that
one thing I love about it is that it's a
very simple question and it's a question
that we should be able to answer
certainly if you're talking about
physics in the vicinity of the event
horizon of the black hole
>> because there we think that the physics
we understand
>> uh well we think we understand the
physics at the horizon not at the
singularity
>> yeah that's the tricky one
>> quantum gravity or something but at the
horizon so that's why
>> at the horizon And we understand the
physics.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow. And for you what is more
interesting the what is happening inside
the bell hole or as you said everything
going outside or even horizon and the
hawking radiation and everything.
>> Well you can even argue about whether
there's such a thing as the inside.
>> Okay which is why it's interesting. And
what we think I mean I think the thing
to say is um I think most physicists or
almost all would say we should
understand
the physics in the vicinity of the
horizon. So so there we're not talking
about you know plank scale energies or
some kind of regime where quantum
gravity should should matter. Mhm.
>> Um so I I think that what whilst the you
know the physics of the the singularity
and that that's clearly beyond us at the
moment but the reason they're
interesting is there is a regime you can
do calculations and it's it's asking
really what is happening when you view
the thing from the outside.
Um that when you start talking about the
interior well we end up with things like
the holographic principle that we can
talk about and a window into as Samuel
said emergence spacetime. So then we
start talking about we start asking
questions such as why is the information
content of a black hole equal to the
surface area of the horizon in square
plank length.
>> Does that suggest that spacetime is
built of things?
>> I should say I mean maybe some of you
should come come in here it's your field
right?
If you say thermodynamics, right? You're
saying these things have temperature and
entropy. Thermodynamics is a statistical
theory. We understand thermodynamics, a
19th century science, certainly the 20th
century in terms of building blocks.
>> Yes.
>> So it's a statistical theory. It's where
you're talking about these properties
like temperature and entropy which arise
from the behavior of smaller building
blocks.
So when you start talking about the
thermodynamics in in the context of
gravity and black holes, you you might
say it's suggestive there are building
blocks of what? Space time,
right? So so that's I think that's one
of the reasons that these this area is
extremely interesting theoretically.
>> Yeah. still like maybe we are just too
daring and asking questions for the 22nd
century because it's very difficult to
connect the theory to observations and
experiments. But imagine you just fell
asleep for 100 years and you wake up and
someone told you that we find out that
either quantum mechanics broke down or
special theory of or relativity in
general broke down. Which of them would
you believe is the first to be updated,
more likely, changed or?
>> I'd guess quantum theory.
>> You would say quantum
>> is the real one. It is the underlying
theory.
the more fundamentals. probably
relativity might break down or the
Laurens symmetry or on some microscopic
scale or
>> not necessarily Lorent symmetry but
possibly I mean I think your field as
you said so emergence spacetime
um I think there's a very famous essay
by
um I can't remember his name Nobel prize
winner in solid state physics um who
wrote an essay about emergent properties
of the universe [clears throat] verse uh
and said it was in the 70s he wrote the
essay I'll remember his name in a moment
but I can't believe I've forgotten
Anderson Anderson it's and and he
pointed out that whilst there can be
emergent behavior
so there can be like I suppose the
classic example is consciousness right
so there's the thing this this prophecy
of the universe which is emerges from
something deeper
>> um you it you you may well not be able
and it may not be appropriate to try to
understand and describe that things in
terms of the underlying theory by which
I would mean particle physics in the
case of cosmology. Right?
>> That's not to say that the phenomena
cannot be explained by the properties of
particles. Indeed, I I strongly believe
that consciousness can, right? It
emerges from that. But it's not the
right language that the language is
neuroscience. And so it may be that the
the language of gravity
may maybe not but it may be that the you
know I space time is it does because it
emerges from something deeper doesn't
mean it's approximate
right maybe maybe that's the right my
view
>> that would be my guess
>> yeah so so general relativity is a very
powerful theory and um even if it turns
out that it's some statistic ical
theory, which it probably is, right? I I
guess I think most most physicists would
probably say that's true.
>> Um, but it's like saying that the laws
of thermodynamics are approximate.
>> They're not really they're good, right?
>> These laws are good laws. They work.
>> So, yeah,
>> if they work, don't change them.
>> Yeah. It doesn't devalue the the the
laws of thermodynamics by saying that
they emerge from a description of well
ultimately from quantum field theory.
>> That's why I didn't ask about second law
of thermodynamic because there's you
cannot really change that. It's very
simple basically a simple consequence of
probability. Um
you you you mentioned the word emergence
and it's also like the name of your your
lecture. So two of the most important
advances in theory in the last 50 years
might be the theory of reormalization
and then the chaos theory which both
teach teach us that on different scales
things are very very different. So maybe
this is the issue that we are still
trying to be very uh reductionist about
how we develop theories and trying to
find the smallest building blocks and
maybe we just we have to change the
perspective
and maybe we won't be able then to
understand it because we understand the
problem by breaking it down into most
fundamental particles and then they are
put together in a way. Oh yeah, maybe
one
>> one example I do talk about an example
in the live show which is um what as
physicists we call spontaneous symmetry
breaking
>> um in the context of the Higs particle
that people will have heard of and um so
that's
an interesting thing it's it's it's
collective behavior it's like a magnet
right so so you you can't understand a
magnet by thinking about one atom
>> [laughter]
>> Right? That's you need well you can't
you kind of but you know the way a ferro
mag works right
>> so so you have these you have ideas of
symmetry breaking and so on. I think
that that
I think you're right what you said which
is that I think that's the modern view
now that you can have dynamics at
different scales
and
>> the so um the thinking I I don't I don't
think it's the right way to think to
think that there are some ways of
looking are more fundamental than
others.
>> I think that's what I'm trying to say. I
think dynamics at different scales is
important.
>> Yeah. Particle physics has been driving
new ideas in physics for decades and
large header collider has completed the
standard model. Uh is it worth building
a new bigger one of
collider or
is there some kind of uh
>> is it worth the money?
>> Yeah. Is it worth the money?
>> Well, the the answer is we don't know.
Uh it's one of the problems in particle
physics. Um the thing about the Large
Hadron Collider was that we knew at that
energy that you would either discover
the Higs particle or the thing that does
the job. Um in fact my most cited paper
in all of my career is is called WW
scattering at the LHC in the absence of
a Ligh Higs particle. Right? So I wrote
a paper saying if there's no light higs
then what what does the job of the Higs
in the most general framework you can
try to understand it [clears throat]
>> now there is a Higs right we discovered
the Higs particle
>> um so um but we knew that that question
would be answered at LHC energies we
knew what the energy was the size of the
collider the problem we face at the
moment is that we don't know for sure
how big that collider has to be, how
powerful it has to be in order to answer
the very deep and profound questions
that we still face. So you said actually
complete the standard model. We kind of
haven't we haven't done that in a way
that there are huge number of problems
with the standard model.
>> Okay.
>> So I'm not physicist.
>> It's it's it's in no way a complete
description of the of the universe. It's
not a good theory. Maybe for me, but but
for gravity out of it, it's it's just a
kind of a mess. It's beautiful in some
ways.
>> Beautiful in other ways.
>> Beautiful mess.
>> Beautiful mess. Yeah. So, um so I think
my view is the answer to your question
is yes. We um and that what part of it
we should build another collider and
part of it is that we do know that in
the absence of anything else the the way
to proceed is to make high precision
measurements of the things that we have
discovered. So the behavior of the Higs
particle for example
>> there are there are questions about the
behavior of the Higs that we don't by
any means understand fully. We don't
know exactly how that particle works. We
c there's a lot of deeper theory we
don't understand. So you can make for
example Higs factories that basically
produce loads and loads and loads of
hits of heart fuel. So we can make
precision measurements
>> in the absence of a clear idea of where
we need to go at higher energy. Um and
the reason I say that I think we should
do that partly is because if when we
stop building things so when we if we
stop building large particle colliders
we lose the ability to build them.
>> So it's a very practical point actually
and we saw that you know when I worked
um quite closely actually with some of
the people who built the large hadron
collider designed and work worked on it.
So during construction I was involved in
some projects to upgrade it and it
involved a lot of work on the collider
itself and that the people that did that
were people who built the previous
collider and the previous collider and
it's very difficult and experience
uh counts for a lot and so I think that
when you look at it globally the way
that we spend our money in scientific
research but also just as a civilization
these are tiny of money huge numbers of
countries. So the idea that you wouldn't
have one of these machines at the energy
frontier
>> at the edge which basically the world
collaborates on which is what happened
with the LAC is to me uh you don't I
don't think you have to say we know
exactly
what this machine will discover. I mean
obviously we never know what it's going
to discover. We're operating on the edge
of our knowledge. But I I would say we
do know that a bigger more powerful one
that could certainly do some things that
we want to do would be a valuable
[clears throat] thing to do.
>> And we see this gap in expertise in uh
uh lunar missions right now. Apollo
missions ended and it's very difficult
to restart them.
>> So
>> yeah, it's a good example. It took it
was a long time, right? We had the
Saturn 5 rocket.
>> It you see how difficult it is to build
those things and launch them with a with
a cadence, right? that you see the
answer missions they
>> what is your guess in this race between
artis and chang who will be first there
>> I I
>> do you have favorite
>> it's very difficult question most of the
experts are like close to 50/50 so which
way
>> yeah and I don't you know honestly if
I'm being really pure about it I don't
care [laughter]
>> I don't care I want
>> that's what I said I don't care somebody
can go the moon. I want us to go to the
moon and beyond and to the stars
ultimately. It's part of the show, part
of the live show at the end is we have
this kind of science fiction thing.
>> Um, which is just a look at what what we
may become.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. What week?
>> I always say the space race between
Soviet Russia and USA was one of the
best spending of uh money that was for
war or something like that because we
got to the moon, we got the
lunar expeditions and so on. So, um I
think this is really great use of the
taxpayers money.
>> Yes. [laughter]
>> Great. And it's like if you're watching
football and you don't favor any of the
teams, you will enjoy the match every
time. If you just f one of the teams,
half of the times you will be
>> you just want to watch the football.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> There's a kind of serious point though,
which is that um and I do talk about
this in the show. I I I talk about life
in the universe, number of civilizations
per galaxy, you know, those kind of
questions. We don't know the answer to
these questions, but we have some um we
have some observations and the the
observations are that we don't see any
sign of any other civilizations
currently in the Milky Way galaxy.
That's an observation. It's often called
the Fermy paradox. And so I do make the
point, which might be a more
philosophical point, that if it's true,
like if we're the only civilization in
the Milky Way galaxy, then we have the
we have the responsibility to do these
things to to to to for intelligence to
exist in a galaxy of 400 billion sons.
Maybe that's our responsibility. And so
on that level ultimately we have to
start behaving like a single planet a
single civilization.
>> So there's a deeper idea to the there's
a deeper reason I say I don't care who
does it. I I my I hope that in the
future we we we say well humanity is
doing it.
>> I I do hope because otherwise what's the
alternative? Yeah, it might it may seem
a bit sort of fanciful to think, well,
can't we all just get along? But
ultimately, maybe the future of
intelligence in the Milky Way galaxy
depends on us getting along and behaving
as a single civilization on a single
planet.
>> Yeah. Interesting because
life follows from the laws of the
universe. But it's something completely
different. Like you can be studying
stars your entire life, but you cannot
understand humans in the same way. It's
like something completely different. So
worth not only preserving but well
building upon it. You are coming to
central Europe shortly and there is a
great book called uh exact thinking in
demented times and it's about have you
read the book?
>> No. It's about the era era between uh
the world wars in central Europe where
everyone was getting very stupid and
confused about a lot of stuff but also
like the amount of scientific knowledge
that was exchanged in cafeterias in
Vienna and etc. It was it was amazing.
This is the name of the book exact
thinking in demented times.
>> Yeah. And now I feel we are doing
something similar like as a society we
seem to be very stupid on some levels
like ignoring climate change and etc.
And then you watch scientific news and
the discoveries we are making in
biochemistry and understanding human
genome understanding universe like you
mentioned verbin telescope there is
Nancy Grey Roman telescope launching
shortly and like the amount of telescope
or the level of Hubble
coming in this year only it's just
amazing. So
>> yeah,
>> how do you think about this as a as a
whole as a society we are maybe becoming
more stupid but if you look at the
scientific breakthroughs and we should
be getting more I don't know civilized
and and clever. So how do you think
about this and what is the role of
scientists in making the world smarter
again? Well, that that's a great
question because as you said, so we're
it appears we're seeing history repeat
itself in some sense. Actually, there's
um I I just I'm going to give you this
quote. I was thinking about this just
before we started the podcast. I was
reading a book which is a kind of an old
science fiction book by um called Star
Maker. Have you read that book? It was
written in the 1930s.
And in the um
>> Olaf Stapleton wrote it and it's um
Arthur C. Clark had said it was one of
the most profound or the most profound
book of science fiction ever written. So
I thought that's interesting.
>> I'll read it.
>> But there's a the in in the
introduction. So in the 1930s he starts
exactly as you started with that
question. He says we're in a what a mess
we're making. It's a frightening world.
I think it's 1937 he wrote the book. And
but then he said uh in the introduction
he says but perhaps the attempt to see
our turbulent world against a background
of stars may after all increase not
lessen the significance of the present
human crisis
>> which I I love it because it's you know
he's saying that maybe the answer to our
question is to widen our perspective
>> to see our problems against the
background of stars and and to your
point so obviously It went wrong in the
1930s, right? We It went wrong. We
didn't do that in the 1950s.
What you see is scientists particularly
people like Richard Feman and Robert
Oppenheimer who'd worked on the
Manhattan project and so seen what the
power of our knowledge can do when
deployed let's say wrongly or when
deployed for for violent purposes let's
say
>> they'd seen what it can do and so they
argued very strongly that scientists
this I remember Feman says it in a in in
an essay he wrote in 1954 called the
value of science. He says that the most
valuable thing we can do as scientists
is to talk about um how knowledge is not
to be feared but welcomed and discussed.
I remember that quote was in there and
to say we have to talk about the value
of not knowing and admitting there are
things that we do not know and admitting
there are problems for the future,
problems that will be solved in the
future. So we don't know everything. Now
what what he's saying is don't think
you're right. Right? Don't ever believe
that you're absolutely right. And you
see it because that was the obviously
the problem. It's the problem when you
get conflict. I strongly believe it. It
political conflict. It's because people
think they're right. It's their absolute
view that they're convinced that this is
the way to do it. And Feman writes in
that book, that essay in the 50s, having
been deeply affected by the Manhattan
projects and the atom bomb that this is
what we have to avoid. We have to
understand that there are different
points of view and different ways of
living and crucially, we don't have the
answers to all the questions. That's the
way to make progress and it's the way to
make peaceful progress. Mhm.
>> And so we've done it before so that we
could do a lot worse than go back and
read what people like Fman and
Oenheimimer and others were writing in
the 1950s after the experience of the
1940s
>> when I had first uh first experience
with such a destruction uh you made
quite a leap back to the Kepler book
because the book also ended that I don't
know Uh I thought so very nice coming
back.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Well, he actually says um I think he's
saying it's because it's it's written to
his benefactor who's the you know who
was paying and I think he says he almost
says it is a puzzle to him. He says I
don't know in my translation of the book
I don't know how good a translation it
is because it's strange to me because he
says I'm knocking on the doors of
chemistry and I go would you would you
have written that? Would you know? But
that's what it says in my translation.
It says, "I don't know."
>> So, and it says, "I leave it to you."
And I like to read that as to the
reader. I lead it, but I think it might
be to his benefactor, actually. But it's
a puzzle. It's I leave it to you. I'm
knocking on the doors. I don't have
enough knowledge. It's It's a radical
idea.
>> Wow.
>> Radical idea of not knowing everything.
>> Yeah.
>> But for today audience, it's
unimaginable.
>> But this is the tickling of the unknown.
What the drive scientist? Yeah,
>> we go to the border of the knowledge and
we feel that we don't know this and for
a few seconds you will be the first
person to know and then you will add
other knows and then the border moves a
little bit. So this is what drives that
ahead.
So maybe we scientists should also show
that not knowing isn't showing like a
weakness. It's part of part of moving
ahead. Without it, you cannot move from
the place where you are standing right
now.
>> It's exactly what Fineman says in this
wonderful essay at the end. It's the
most valuable thing of all.
>> He says he says actually he says
>> he says we have to admit that we don't
know but in doing that
we will we may have found the open
channel. That's what he calls it. The
open channel
>> is that that one idea.
>> I love that. the open channel that that
sounds really profound. Uh Brian uh we
should end in few minutes. Uh we uh I
can imagine that you always have a lot
of scientific question and so on. I will
ask you some personal questions if you
don't mind. Do you like football or any
kind of sport because they were
>> Yeah. So I I grew up in a place called
Oldm which is near Manchester and um the
our football team there is called Oldm
Athletic and that's where I used to go.
I grew up next to the ground. I had a
season ticket there so I used to go all
the time and we were successful in the
19 sort of 1990s. Um early 1990s we were
very successful. We were founder members
of the Premier League. So we were away
Manchester United and Liverpool and all
those clubs.
>> Not Man City because they were in the
second division at the time, right?
>> So you were better than Man City.
>> And then we got relegated all the way
out of the football league. And so we
kind of
>> little town, a little club, but now
we're back in again. So we got promoted
last year. So we're beginning to make
our way up again.
>> So yeah, so older athletic are my
>> Do you find time to watch some uh
matches or do you just
passively
>> occasionally when I because I so I teach
at Manchester. So I teach first year
relativity and quantum mechanics
actually at the moment at the University
of Manchester.
>> So when I'm up there, I try and go to a
game. Oh, great.
>> Most of the episode, my mom was sitting
nearby. She's a huge fan of yours and
she asked me to ask you something about
music. So, give one musical
recommendation, one album you like to
listen to right now because your shows
are not only visual but also like for
all senses. So,
>> yeah,
>> give us one recommendation.
>> Um, well, I'll tell you something about
the the show. So we um that we I talk
about the Voyager spacecraft in the show
because the Voyager spacecraft is the
50th anniversary of the launch next
year,
>> half a century in space.
>> And uh do you know the the musician PJ
Harvey who's been a hero of mine for a
long time?
>> So she came to one of the shows I did on
the last tour and she she's really
interested in all the questions we've
been discussing. So I said to her, "Can
we do a song? Can we can we do a song
for the show about Voyager?" And she
said, "Yes." Right. So we we um recorded
this song that she wrote about Voyager.
I had this idea that if it's from 50
years in space, if it's looking back at
the Earth, knowing all the things it's
learned on its voyage and it's had half
a century to think, what would it say to
us? And so she wrote this song and we
recorded it and it's in the show
>> and I I love it. So that's at the moment
I would say and it's on you can listen
to it. It's on Spotify and elsewhere,
right? So DJ Harvey's Voyager I and
you'll hear it at the start of the
second act of the show
>> and she has a great album called Let
England Shake. So
>> hopefully
>> very famous album.
>> Yeah,
>> let let Bratisy Slava shake when you
come here and hopefully people will be
melting as Kepler's snowflakes.
Yeah,
>> I cannot wait on the 9th of September
that we will be there with Samuel
somewhere in the audience and we will
listen and uh enjoy everything that is
uh happening on the stage. So even music
I didn't know that. So
>> and you can find all the details in the
episode description. You can find link
to the tickets. So see you there in ina.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. And Brian,
thank you for having chat with us. It
was amazing. and thank you for a little
bit of secret. You are my personal hero.
So [laughter]
>> for me that was that was like amazing.
>> I'm interested that you're you work on
on on remnants of black holes. I know I
know Tom Banks who wrote my favorite
quantum mechanics textbook at the moment
which is a very badly titled
introductory quantum mechanics which it
really isn't but I think he's a a
remnant person. I think he's a
>> I think so. Well, we can discuss when
you come to Bratislava.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We should grab a beer. Okay.
Have a nice day and thank you very much
again.